No record. There's no trace of it.
Completely
anonymous.
You don't have to show any ID or
anything.
So, that's how they transfer drug money.
That's how terrorist groups finance
themselves.
But the Dubaians
have a have a beat on it.
So, that's you were there to educate
them on that?
>> No, I was there to ask them how the heck
do you do this?
>> Oh.
Yeah, and they were like, "Well,
there are a lot of threats that take
place at the same time.
Yeah, like we can beat you on the soles
of your feet with a baseball bat
or you can give us copies of your ledger
every day at the end of the work day.
>> [cough]
>> The Middle East. Your choice. Your
choice, that's right.
So, the you had the US sorted out the
hawala problem
at this time because I would assume that
terrorists were using it in the US?
>> and they continue to use it. The The US
Hawalas are easy enough to infiltrate.
Um, any FBI agent can go to this Arabic
bakery and they probably already have
gone to the Arabic bakery in Bethesda,
Maryland and said, "Look, you know,
we're going to [__] you up or you're
going to give us access to your books."
It's The US government is far more
worried about uh cryptocurrency. Mhm.
Yeah, that's why, you know, doing my
taxes this most recent uh
iteration,
they asked me quick and asked me three
different times if I had bought or sold
crypto.
Like, how many Why three times? It's
because they're so worried about
terrorist financing and money
laundering.
Like, have you bought or sold crypto?
Are you sure you haven't bought or sold
crypto?
Maybe you forgot. You want to think
about it a minute. Have you bought or
sold crypto?
I'm like, "No, I don't have any crypto."
But they're very worried about it.
Well, what I was going to ask is because
the way the way the blockchain and I
don't know much about it, but the way
it's written so to speak, they don't
they don't have any ends. They don't?
Legitimately, they do not have any ends.
No. And that's why the likes of Coinbase
just open their books to the to the
government.
Cuz they don't want to be implicated in
terrorist financing and money
laundering.
Mhm.
So, um
to come back to the Mossad
>> Mhm.
I told this for for people that listened
to the had a historian Rick Rick Spence.
He's a He's You know Rick Spence?
Um so, for people that heard me tell the
story on that podcast, sorry about that,
but I want to get John's take on it and
you'll hear why. So, um there was a
This was a a documentary that was that
came out of Israel. So, it was all on
the up and up. And there was a Mossad
officer that
told the story about um
they recruited an asset who, let's say
he was like some sort of, you know, goat
herder or something in, I believe, let's
I think it was Syria.
And so, they recruit the guy and
eventually the Palestinians come to the
guy and they wanted to recruit him
because his he was in close proximity to
the Israeli border.
>> Sure. Um again, I don't know if it was
Syria, but whatever, let's just say it
was. So, the Palestinians come to him
and then he goes and tells uh the Mossad
and they're like, "Hey, I got approached
by these guys. They want to know about
some either border setup or movement of
the IDF." And what the Mossad said is,
"Okay, give me the information because
let's just assume what you can see, they
can see. And it's all out there. Build a
relationship give me the information."
Gives it to them.
So, then they come back to him and they
say, "Okay, we want you to find a spot
in the border wall for us to cross into
Israel." Oh boy. So, he goes to the
Mossad and he tells them this and they
say, "Okay, let's let's go find a spot
in the border wall together. And then
when they come through, there'll be a
warm welcome waiting for them."
So, they pick the spot. He goes and
tells the Palestinians and they say,
"Okay, great. Thanks." The night before
the operation, they tell him they say,
"Oh yeah, and by the way, as an
insurance policy, you're coming with
us."
>> Oh, [__]
>> tells the Mossad this. And they said,
"Well, if you If you say no, they'll get
spooked, and they'll either you'll blow
your cover, or they'll kill you." Mhm.
So, go with them, and when you cross the
border, hit the deck, and we have ways
to make sure that you don't get shot.
And essentially, that was all [__]
And the way that the Mossad officer
described it was sacrificing a pawn off
the chessboard.
And so,
I don't say that to illustrate the fact
that, "Oh my god, the Mossad is so bad."
Like, intelligence is is a dirty game. I
think we're all well aware of that. But,
the point What I
got from that is
why the hell would they be saying this?
Number one, to to speak to the
ruthlessness of the Mossad, sure. The
mystique, I think that that is
beneficial to an intelligence agency.
But,
>> a Palestinian,
>> That's what I'm saying. Why would you
want to work with any agency?
>> Yeah. Do they burn assets like that? Oh,
I'm sure that they do.
I'm sure that they do. But, that's in no
no other
no other intelligence service would
would have sent somebody sent a
recruited asset to his death like that.
That doesn't make any sense.
But, the Israelis are not like anybody
else.
They're not. It's just another
Palestinian
to them.
So, what's an example operationally like
that that you could think of when you're
like, "The Israelis are different"?
In almost everything that the Israelis
do.
When I was The first time I went on
Piers Morgan, I debated a former
director of the Mossad.
And the guy just couldn't stop
chuckling all through the I mean, it was
ridiculous.
I said things like,
"The Israelis spy on the United States."
"Oh, no, no, not since Jonathan
Pollard."
And I said, "Well, Jonathan Pollard was
caught in 1985, and you were spying on
the United States in 1998,
you know, or 2004.
No comment.
It's like, what what is that? We would
never We're not permitted to spy on the
Israelis.
We're not permitted.
The the potential for blowback is
is outrageous. Can you imagine if we
spied on the Israelis and got caught?
Every member of Congress would be
demanding the CIA director's head. Do
you think that we really don't spy on
the Israelis?
That was verboten when I was there.
I was surprised to hear you say that in
that interview because I figured it's
this
gentleman's game, so to speak.
>> Mhm.
With most other places, post-9/11, you
know, we developed the Five Eyes and we
don't spy on each other in the Five
Eyes.
Uh the Five Eyes being US, UK, Canada,
Australia, New Zealand.
You know, we literally sit next to each
other in each other's headquarters. I
remember when George Tenet ordered us to
open the files, he said, and he meant
literally open the files. And so we've
had this Five Eyes relationship ever
since.
And of course, we have very, very close
relationships with other countries. Not
a ton, but
a lot.
But the Israelis are special.
Yeah, we do not spy on the Israelis.
What about the Brits?
Like
I don't know why. Do they have a
reputation of being
I don't want to
Not ruthless necessarily, but what
What was your experience with the Brits?
>> The The Brits are very good at what they
do. And the One of the reasons why
they're very good Well, there are
several reasons. One, because they're
everywhere, right? Most of these
countries were colonies of the UK at one
time or another. But they're also very
good because they have only a fraction
of the bureaucracy that we do.
If we have an idea for an operation or
for a covert action program, we have to
go through 6 months and a dozen layers
of permissions, you know, lawyers from
this office and lawyers from that
office. The Brits want to do something,
they just say, "Hey, we're going to do
this." And then they go out and do it.
I remember a boss of mine in in
counterterrorism just
saying,
"I I was on my way out to London. We
were doing a joint operation." And he
said, "Boy, I I wish we were like the
Brits. If they want to do something, a
week later they're doing it."
And I mentioned that to the Brits one
time. And my counterpart said, "Yeah,
but we wish we had your budget." Mhm.
And I said, "Yeah, you guys can never
touch our budget.
Nobody can."
Um
this is completely unrelated, but I
don't know why I thought of this. Didn't
you do an op uh with Billy Waugh? Oh,
yeah.
Yeah.
In the Emirates.
Again, you'd say what that was? I
cannot, unfortunately. It was
It was We did two things. We were there
to do some training classes. But we were
there for a sensitive electronic kind of
thing.
But Billy was
Billy was bonafide American hero.
Truly.
A real hero.
Yeah, I mean, if people aren't that
aren't familiar, he was uh he was former
I mean, [__] man. He was one of the uh
the Vietnam SF guys. He was a Green
Beret. And then he was he served at the
CIA for like 40 years or something.
Yeah, he was in World War II,
Korea, and Vietnam.
And to the best of my recollection, had
17 Purple Hearts. He had a He had a
personalized license plate that said 17
hits.
And I said, "Billy, that's
that's a joke, right?"
And he said, "No, it's not a joke. I got
17 Purple Hearts." I said, "That has to
be like Guinness Book of World Records
kind of thing." And he says He had a
terrible, terrible, filthy mouth. And
he's like, "Nah, there's some sorry-ass
son of a [__] from North Carolina got
18."
But he used to He used to tell stories,
too. Like he told told this story once
about
about being shot down behind North
Korean lines.
And he would forget that he had told me
the story. And so he would tell it over
and over and over. And then the final
time that he that he told me the story,
he was naked, first of all.
Secondly, um he he came upon a cow in a
pasture and he slit the cow's uh
artery and drank the blood um for
nourishment because he was starving. I
go, "That was in Apocalypse Now.
>> [laughter]
>> That wasn't you.
That was from Apocalypse Now." And he's
like, "Ah, it still makes for a good
story."
Oh, that's great.
He was a good guy. Was Was he uh Did he
even have ground branch back then or was
he just a contractor or
Yeah, he was just a contractor.
He was a contractor and he was fearless.
I mean, when I knew him, he was already
well into his 70s.
And, you know, died in his 90s. Never
had children.
His He was deeply in love with his wife,
but she had died of cancer. So he was
alone. And then 9/11 hit. And what else
is there to live for? He's got no kids.
Bought a house in
It was like uh
Yeah, friendly
friendly's town or
or Sunshineville or It had some stupid
made-up name in Florida.
Um
I can't remember the name of it. And he
had a niece who lived in Las Vegas and
she she ghost wrote his autobiography.
And I was glad somebody did cuz
his stories,
whether or not they were a little
embellished, his stories are an
important part of modern American
history. And there really needed to be a
written record of them.
Yeah. Niceville. Niceville. That's the
>> Something American.
>> Yeah. Niceville, Florida.
Were you at the agency when they stood
up the GRS program? No, I had already
gone.
I had already gone, but I was dating a
woman at the time whose soon-to-be
ex-husband was in GRS, and she said, "My
husband's a GRS officer." I said,
"What's GRS?"
She looked at me kind of funny, and she
told me, and I said, "Oh, [__] They've
made it official?"
So, what was it before they made it
official?
>> It was just like, "Hey, you doing
anything for the next week? We're going
to need for you to do this thing. Don't
tell anybody."
Yeah, now it's an office.
But, wasn't it wasn't it stood up to be
like security for case officers? Mm,
security for leaders more than case
Well, no, that's not true. Security for
case officers, yes, especially as it
related to operating in the green zone
in Baghdad. That That's where most of
them were doing their work.
Cuz the green zone was easily
infiltrated. Yeah, moving from point A
to point B, you took your life in your
hands every time.
Those guys
I mean, you have to be a brave son of a
gun to to do a job like that.
I mean, you can say about a lot of
different agency jobs, "Oh, that job's
not for everybody." That job?
You really have to be fearless.
You really do.
Cuz your your job is literally
to throw your body in front of the other
guy
so the other guy doesn't get killed and
can complete the meeting.
Yeah, thankless.
I can't remember who it was. It was
somebody who was in GRS was talking
about Yemen
and how Yemen was like a spy craft
playground.
>> I've been to Yemen five times.
In your prior life?
>> Mhm. In what context?
Each time was for a different thing. Um,
the first time I went
it was kind of funny. Um, the first time
I went, there were two Yemens.
Right? There was the Republic of Yemen,
North Yemen, and then the People's
Democratic Republic of Yemen, which was
a Soviet satellite state.
And um
things were looking really good the
first time I went. The two Yemens in the
process of merging and becoming one
unified Yemen. People were literally
dancing in the streets.
This uh I I went that first time from
Jeddah. I was I was in Jeddah, Saudi
Arabia, and uh two friends of mine were
stationed in in Sana'a. And so they
said, "Hey, you know, the prophet's
birthday is Monday, so it's a 3-day
weekend. You want to come down to to
Yemen? We'll hang out." I said, "Yeah,
I'd never been to Yemen." So I just flew
down. We had a great time.
Second time I went,
this one unified Yemen thing, it's not
working out the way they thought it was.
And so
there weren't really any benefits, and
the North Yemenis were trying to
dominate the South Yemenis, and it just
wasn't good.
The third time I went, they're launching
Scud missiles at each other, right? And
then the it was the first civil war, and
then the North defeated the South. And
then the vice president, um Ali Abdullah
Saleh,
uh
he was a South Yemeni. He fled to South
fled to Oman
to save himself.
And the fourth time I went,
it was it was
grim.
Where
it wasn't safe to stay anywhere except
the Marriott, which had 30-ft blast
walls all around it.
The last time I went, I was with the
Senate Foreign Relations Committee.
And
we were just getting ready to close the
embassy and evacuate everybody.
So I go there. I'm staying at the
Marriott,
and
security is crazy heavy.
It's actually kind of funny. I
I alluded to this in a Senate report
that I wrote. Um
but
I I had never seen security like this
anywhere.
And
there are these guys
right outside the lobby of the hotel,
and they've got machine guns, like
obviously, like, you know, MAC-9s,
MAC-10s,
and they're speaking English, American
English.
And
I said to the to the boab, the the
doorman,
I said uh "Men who know who who's here?"
And he goes
"V VIP."
Like that. I said V VIP who? Mrs.
Clinton?
He goes "No, it's a man."
I said uh
"Is it uh Mr. Cheney?" Or no, it wasn't
Cheney, it was Biden. He was vice
president at the time.
Uh
Biden? And he says
"No." I said "Who is it?" He goes "I
don't know."
So then I hear um "The package is
moving. The package is moving." So I'm
just standing there. And then here comes
the V VIP and he looks at me and he goes
"Hello, John."
And I said "Hello, Steve."
Cappas, the deputy director of CIA. And
he gets in his limo and I go "What, no
ride for me?"
>> [laughter]
>> And he drives away like a six-car
convoy.
I had to wait for my, you know,
one poorly armored 10-year-old
Volkswagen to come and pick me up. It
was so rude. Anyway,
I was on the CIA [__] list by then.
>> Yeah. So
um the reason why it was so bad, just a
couple of days before I arrived, a group
of
well, about a week before I arrived, a
group of
of six South Korean diplomats had
arrived to talk to the Yemeni government
about a development project. And on the
road from the airport to the hotel, they
were ambushed by Al-Qaeda and they were
all assassinated.
And so a few days after that, the South
Korean government sent a group of South
Korean intelligence officers to
investigate the terrorist attack.
And they were ambushed on the road to
the hotel and they were all
assassinated.
The Koreans just shut the embassy down
and evacuated everybody.
It's it's grim.
It really is. And there's no hope in
sight.
Yeah, I remember hearing about there was
a I mean obviously a lot of terror going
on in Yemen but wasn't there um
I want to say it was some I think it was
the Saudi intelligence head that almost
got killed by the guy with the bomb up
his ass.
>> Yeah, that was uh the sha- that was
Prince Muhammad bin Nayef. But wasn't
that directed by uh the American guy in
Yemen all on Awlaki or whatever the hell
his name was? That was the rumor. I
never believed that to be the case
because Awlaki was more of a
propagandist than he wasn't operational
in any way.
You know, I met him.
Yeah, in fact
I was the only
CIA officer. Well, here here's what
happened.
I'm in Arabic training in 1993.
And our in the CIA language school
and the the instructor says, "We're
going to go out on a field trip today.
We're going to go to Falls Church,
Virginia and that's where all the Arabs
live.
So, we're going to go to um the Quran
store. There's a there's a store in the
strip mall in Falls Church that just
sells Qurans.
And apparently they do perfectly fine
for themselves. So, we're going to go to
the Quran store, then we're going to go
to the Arabic grocery store, and then
we're going to go to the shish kebab
restaurant, but you can't speak English.
And then after lunch, we're going to go
to the mosque. There's a gigantic
mosque on uh Route 7 in Falls Church.
We're going to go to the mosque and
we're going to talk about Islam, but you
can't speak English.
We're like, "Cool." And we had done this
a couple times. We went to the zoo to
learn the names of the animals in
English and then we had you know
we did all different kinds of field
trips.
So, we go go do this thing and we learn
the the word for you know fava beans and
we learn the word for newspaper and
we're trying to talk to the shopkeepers.
We order lunch in Arabic. And then we go
to the the mosque. Well, Anwar al-Awlaki
was the Imam of the mosque.
And
8 years later
that's where the 9/11 hijackers prayed
the night before 9/11.
Anwar al-Awlaki was born in um New
Mexico.
He was Yemeni. His father was the Yemeni
ambassador to the United States who went
back to Yemen to become the Minister of
Agriculture.
Solidly pro-American.
Anwar
was born in New Mexico, raised as an
American spoke English without any kind
of accent. Just spoke English like you
and I speak English.
But self-radicalized
during the Soviet occupation of
Afghanistan. And then joined al-Qaeda
before 9/11, in like '98 or '99.
So
after 9/11, I just I mentioned
offhandedly one day
"Oh, al-Awlaki? I met him." People like,
"What?"
I said, "Yeah.
And in my Arabic class, we went to the
mosque. And he gave us a tour of the
mosque, and we had a Q&A, and then he
gave us tea, and next thing I know,
security's down. Like, "We need to go
over this from the beginning." Cuz
everybody else had left the agency by
then. All the other students had moved
on to other careers, and the the
instructor had retired, and I was the
only one left who had actually met
al-Awlaki. I'm like, "Guys, it was one
afternoon. I don't know what I can tell
you that's going to be of any
operational value."
But then I did go to Yemen.
And um funny thing, you know, I have
this
relationship with the FBI, right? So I
go I go to Yemen. And nobody in the CIA
would speak to me.
I was with the Senate Foreign Relations
Committee.
So I go to see the FBI, the Legat, the
Legal Attaché. So I walk in, and I I
knock on the door, and I said, "Hey."
And the guy says, "Ah, John Kiriakou,
born August 9th, 1964, Sharon,
Pennsylvania. Graduated from New Castle
High School, New Castle, Pennsylvania.
Bachelor's degree in Middle Eastern
Studies, Master's in Legislative Affairs
from George Washington University." I
go, "Very funny.
Very funny." He says,
"You're going to do me a favor."
And I said, "Really? What favor's that?"
He said, "You're going to go back to
your Congressional Committee, and you're
going to get me funding for two more
slots out here." And I said, "Really?
What's in it for me?"
He says,
"I'll give you a classified briefing."
I said, "Okay, I'll take that deal."
So, I I did get him slots for two more
FBI agents, but in the course of that
conversation, I said, "So, what do you
do? Sit here and play with your balls,
or you out looking for Anwar al-Awlaki?"
And he said, "Al-Awlaki, I know when
al-Awlaki blows a fart," he says.
He said, "I know al-Awlaki's location to
within 3 ft, 24 hours a day."
And I said, "Why don't you take him
out?" He said, "Well, that's
that's the other side of the hall's
job."
And then, sure enough, couple months
later, they blow him to a thousand
pieces.
Uh
Who was the classified briefing on?
Al-Awlaki. Oh, okay. Yeah.
I don't know. Uh well, actually,
speaking of uh like the Saudis, uh
didn't We didn't cover this last time,
but didn't Abu Zubaydah's diary
have the names and phone numbers of
three of them? Three princes.
>> But then, something weird happened to
them?
We went to the Saudis, and we said,
"Look,
there there are three princes in Abu
Zubaydah's address book with their
personal cell phone numbers.
You need to take care of this, or we're
going to take care of it. And you're not
going to like the way we do it."
Next thing you know, like magic,
one of them dies on the operating table
while getting bariatric bypass surgery.
One is killed in a one-car accident on
the Riyadh to Jeddah highway.
And one of them goes camping in the
desert and dies of thirst.
Mhm.
And then they said, "Listen, you know,
we wanted to help you out with those
three princes, but they
they don't exist anymore."
So, were the Saudis friends?
In that context, I would argue that they
weren't because that means that none of
those guys are available for
interrogation. Ah.
It was better to murder their own
relatives
than to allow them to be interrogated
by the CIA.
Probably because they had information up
there that the Saudis didn't want
>> Mhm. the CIA to find out. Mhm.
I've been in relatively close touch
recently with Abu Zubaydah's attorneys.
Um
I asked one if he would agree to sit for
my podcast, and he immediately said yes.
So, we had a long conversation
about Abu Zubaydah.
And at the end of it, we'd stopped
recording and I said, "Would you do me a
favor? Would you tell Abu Zubaydah" They
don't call him Abu Zubaydah, they call
him Zayn. Zayn al-Abidin Muhammad Husayn
is his actual name.
I just by force of habit I call him Abu
Zubaydah. So, I said, "Would you tell
him that I send my best.
I'm sorry for what our country did to
him.
I know that he's innocent and that he
should be released.
And I hope he is someday."
And the attorney says, "Actually,
he has a message for you.
I told him I was going to talk to you
today."
He goes,
"He says first,
his recollection of the night you caught
him is different from yours."
>> [laughter]
>> I said, "Undoubtedly, it is different."
Um but that's okay.
His recollection is probably I stood up
and I told them, you know. Anyway, um
he says uh
the night that you blew the whistle on
the torture program, a friendly guard at
Guantanamo went to his cell and said, "A
CIA man went public today about what
happened to you." And he said it was the
first time he had experienced a
sensation of hope.
That was December 2007. And he says he
wanted me to tell you he hopes that the
two of you can have dinner someday as
free men.
I said, "Tell him I send my best and
I'll pray for that."
Wouldn't hold my breath on that one. No.
You know, one of the sad things about
that as a postscript is he was
weeks from being released at the end of
the Biden administration. They had They
had made the decision to release him.
They were in negotiations with different
countries to take him. They couldn't
find a country that would agree to take
him.
And then Trump won.
And so
he's not going anywhere.
All right. So
Did uh So I'll just I'll I made some
notes uh throughout that um
we can come back to. So um
I forget what it was. When Did they ever
teach you Oh, right. Worst case uh as a
CIA officer, right? You pitch a You
pitch an agent. He flips the table over
and says, "I'm going to report you."
Other worst case is, you know, you're
operating abroad. You are brought in by
the authorities of that country or, you
know, God forbid a terrorist
organization or something. Did they
teach you guys um
counter-interrogation or SERE?
Not SERE.
But counter-interrogation techniques,
yeah. You know, we even have coffee mugs
with the admit nothing, deny everything,
make counter-accusations. Uh If you're
If you're overseas and you're under
official cover, all you have to say is,
"Look, diplomatic immunity. Call the
American Embassy." That's it. Done. I'm
not saying another word.
Call the American embassy.
If you're kidnapped
by a terrorist organization, that's an
entirely different issue. You know, Bill
Buckley, the CIA learned so many
lessons, painful, terrible lessons with
the kidnapping of Bill Buckley in 1984.
Bill Buckley was the CIA station chief
in Beirut and was was kidnapped by
um elements of Palestinian Islamic
Jihad. They kidnapped him in the parking
garage of his apartment building.
And um
they knew that he had a tracker, a
tracking device in his belt buckle. So,
the first thing they did is they just
took the belt off of him and threw it
out the car window.
And so, we didn't have any idea where he
was.
About a month later,
the American embassy in
Athens receives a VHS tape
showing Buckley being tortured. And he's
begging the agency to help him.
And then um another like six
months pass or four months, whatever it
is.
It's out there in in the media.
Uh the American embassy in Rome receives
a video tape. And he's like just hanging
from a hook and there's snot coming out
of his mouth and he's mumbling something
that you can't understand.
And then we had a source tell us that
they just executed him after a while.
And um we were able to get his body
back.
And then
the people who kidnapped him from from
Pidge, the Palestinian Islamic Jihad,
no longer exist.
So,
we took care of them
and then got the body back. And he's
buried at Arlington Cemetery. Now, I go
every once in a while. I live walking
distance from Arlington Cemetery. So, I
go see the the CIA station chief from
Athens and go see Buckley
and um Mike Spann and people like that.
So, uh we learned a lot of lessons
there.
Yeah.
Did you know Mike Spann? Yeah, sure.
Wasn't he of the Ground Branch guys that
was uh the immediately in in Drawbreaker
on the ground?
>> Yeah.
We we worked 10 ft away from each other.
We're in the same that bullpen area.
Yeah, good guy, nice guy, good family
man.
Yeah.
Looking back at what happened to him,
I can only imagine the panic that must
have set in. He was He was at
Lashkar-e-Taiba I'm sorry um
He was at uh
Oh [__] I forget the name of the fort
in northern Afghanistan.
We had just caught um
John Walker Lindh, the American Taliban,
and uh
The name's going to come to me. And
there was an uprising among all these
Taliban and Al-Qaeda prisoners we had
caught, and
Mike and a couple of other guys were
were soon overwhelmed. They ended up
just opening fire on these guys, and
they ran out of bullets, and then he was
stomped to death.
That's how he died.
They stomped him to death.
Mhm.
>> [clears throat]
>> Like deliberately by
>> Oh yeah.
Oh yeah.
I can only imagine
the panic.
What was the name of that fort?
I can't remember anymore.
But he he died a hero's death.
Man, the absolute balls on those guys.
>> Mhm. And that was what?
Before the end of September, right? Or
the very beginning of October?
>> beginning, I think of October.
No, that's not right, because the
uprising
was to the best of my recollection on
the
on the 30th of November, maybe?
I think it was the 30th of November
2001.
Yeah.
And so um again, another thing we didn't
talk about is uh
your we didn't really get into your time
with with Carey, but I think there was
one
funny story that you didn't tell here
that involved the CIA and well, funny's
maybe the wrong word choice, but the
with the whole Dasht-e Leili thing.
Dasht-e Leili?
Yeah. So,
on November 30th and December 1st of
2001,
2,000 Taliban soldiers gave up en masse
to the Northern Alliance
at Dasht-e Leili in northern
Afghanistan.
And the Northern Alliance
came to us and said,
"We can't hold 2,000 prisoners. What
should we do?"
And we told them to
put them in trucks,
truck them out into the desert, and
let's just hold them there out in the
desert until we can divide them up and
send them to jails around the country.
So,
General Abdul Rashid Dostum, who's like
the greatest traitor in the history of
of Afghanistan, he's he's with the
Northern Alliance, then he's with the
Taliban, then he's with the Northern
Alliance again, then he's with the
Taliban again, and he's just a just a
traitor of of the worst ilk.
And um
he was in charge of these prisoners.
So,
they trucked these 2,000 people
jammed into containers
out into the desert.
And one of the 16 survivors
told us that when they opened the
trucks, the bodies fell out like
sardines from a can
because nobody had punched air holes in
the trucks, and there was no food or
water.
And so, almost all 2,000 of them
suffocated.
We always believed Dostum did it on
purpose
because he was that kind of a
psychopath.
So,
Barack Obama promised during the 2008
campaign to investigate the what's
what's now called the Dasht-e Leili
massacre.
And he said, you know, if I'm elected
president, I'm going to order the
National Security Council to begin this
investigation, blah blah blah. Never
happened. Cuz the agency got to him
right away.
Anyway, 2009, I find myself as the
senior investigator on the Senate
Foreign Relations Committee. And a human
rights activist, quite a prominent,
important, well-known human rights
activist calls me and says he needs to
see me privately, like secretly. So, we
meet in a
darkened, unused classroom at Johns
Hopkins University.
I go. I say, "What's up?"
And he says, "You know the Dasht-e Leili
massacre?" I said, "Of course."
He said, "I've got a a witness who has
just come forward. He was 12 at the
time, but he was behind a rock when they
were opening the trucks. We used to call
it the box up.
So, he he had witnessed the sort of
unveiling of the of the containers.
And there were
two guys there wearing blue jeans and
black shirts and speaking English.
And I said, "Well, I mean, who's in
Dasht-e Leili, Afghanistan
on December the 1st, 2001, wearing a
black T-shirt and blue jeans and
speaking English?"
So, this kid had become an American
citizen.
He had held this inside all these years.
Approached him and said, "Look, I don't
know if this is important, but this is
what I saw."
So,
I went to Kerry
and I said,
"I met with this human rights activist,
whom he knew.
And uh
I said, you know, the president did say
he was going to reopen the case and get
to the bottom of Dasht-e Leili." Kerry
says, "Okay, write a letter to the
agency. Ask if there were agency
personnel on the ground.
So, I write a letter.
And uh we auto pen it, you know, John
Kerry, chairman.
Like 6 weeks pass.
And a colleague of mine walks in and he
says, "Hey, uh you got a response from
the agency to your letter." I said, "I
just checked my mail an hour ago. I
didn't see any response from the
agency."
He said they classified it top secret,
so it's downstairs in the vault. And at
the time, I only had a secret clearance.
I said, "Well, what did it say?"
And he said, uh "Says go [__] yourself."
I was like, "Oh, okay. So, that's how
they want to play it."
So, I was going to go guns blazing,
right? Call the Washington Post, tell
the story, and then Kerry calls me. He's
like,
"Stop.
Stop." I said, "Come on now." I said,
"The president specifically said he
wanted us to get to the bottom of
Dasht-e Leili." And Kerry says, "Yeah,
and now he doesn't."
So, did the agency know that it was you
on his staff?
>> Absolutely.
100% yes.
>> [laughter]
>> Go [__] yourself. I was like, "All
right. All right."
I can call the post, too.
>> [laughter]
>> Yeah. Um
anything else stand out from your time
with Kerry that you don't typically talk
about? I was so excited to work for John
Kerry and he turned out to be a coward.
Just a mainstream nobody.
All he ever talked about was how
desperately he wanted to be Secretary of
State and how he got ripped off and
Hillary Clinton stole his job from him.
There were only two times when I ever
gave John Kerry unsolicited advice.
Once.
It's a little bit of a story. We have
time?
>> yeah.
So, he asked me to write him a speech.
He had a speech writer, but on stuff
that was like really specific to the
Middle East, I did it.
So, he's going to give a speech at
like the Smithsonian Institution or
Council on Foreign Relations, something
I I don't remember anymore. This is
2009.
Let me back up, actually.
So, in in 2008, I had
my own little business. And Mack
McLarty, who had been Bill Clinton's
chief of staff at the White House, Mack
very generously offered me an office and
a part-time secretary in McLarty
Associates. Back then it was Kissinger
McLarty.
I I was very I was very indebted to him.
He was very kind to me.
So, one of the guys on the board of
directors of McLarty was Governor Bill
Richardson,
Congressman Bill Richardson, Secretary
of Energy Bill Richardson, Ambassador to
the United Nations Bill Richardson. And
Bill and I loved each other.
I even voted for him for president in
2008 after he quit race.
And I told him, "Bill, I still voted for
you." Anyway, anyway,
um
we really got along.
And so,
he he comes into my office. Let me think
of the date. It was like
January of 2008.
January, December 2007, something like
that.
And he says to me,
it was Ja- it was No, it wasn't. It was
February of 2008. He says, "Hey, do you
have a minute?" I said, "Of course."
He said, "Something
crazy happened over the weekend." He
said, "I invited Obama to my house
to watch the Super Bowl.
Super Bowl's like first Sunday in
February now.
And um he said, "At halftime, we went
for a walk.
He put his arm around me and he said,
'Bill,
if you can endorse me
and you bring the Hispanic vote,
Secretary of State.'
I said, 'You going to do it?" He goes,
"Of course I'm going to do it." I said,
"Awesome."
He goes, "I want you to be my deputy
chief of staff." I said, "Done. I'll
take it." He He is chief of staff from
when he was governor, really sweet guy.
He was going to be chief of staff. I
said, "I'm in. I'll take it."
So, the months are passing, like, "Oh my
god, I I can't believe and Obama's going
to win and Richardson's going to be
going to be Secretary of State and I'm
going to be ambassador to Greece or, you
know, it's going to be awesome."
November comes, Obama wins.
So, the day after the election, I go
into the office and I said, I go like
this, I go, "Mr. Secretary,
congratulations."
He goes, "Man, I am so excited. I can't
even sleep. I'm so excited."
Couple of weeks later,
I'm in the shower
and I had a radio in my in my, you know,
bathroom, sitting on the on the sink.
And I'm listening to the news station in
DC, WTOP, and they said,
"Former New Mexico Governor Bill
Richardson has been tapped by
President-elect Obama to be Secretary of
Commerce." And I was like, "What?"
So, I get dressed. I go into the office
and I go, "Mr. Secretary,
congratulations." He goes like this, he
goes, "What the [__] do I know about
commerce? Tell me. What the [__] do I
know about commerce?" And I said, "No,
no, no.
We can make something out of this."
>> [laughter]
>> I go, "There's the foreign commercial
service.
I said, "There's the international trade
representative. We can turn this into
something. You do it for the first term
and then Secretary of State in the
second term."
He goes, "I'm so mad, I could explode."
Couple of more weeks pass, same thing,
I'm in the shower.
I got the news on and they said, "Former
New Mexico Governor Bill Richardson has
withdrawn his nomination to be Secretary
of Commerce." I was like, "Fuck."
So, I go in the office and he said, "I
just couldn't do it. I just couldn't do
it." He said, "I honestly have zero
interest in trade. Nothing." I said,
"No, that's cool. I'll figure something
out." Then, I get hired by Kerry.
So, I write the speech with him. One of
the things about Kerry I always hated
is he thinks he's smarter than everybody
else in the room.
And so, you've got this very carefully
scripted speech for him to write
and he'll just start winging it and
meandering all over the place and his
sentences have no verbs in them and you
don't know what the heck he's talking
about or what the point is and then he
can't remember where he left off and
he's like looking at the different
sheets of paper.
I hated when he would do that. So, I
think it was at the Smithsonian we must
have been.
And he's reading the speech, he's giving
the speech, you know, the Middle East,
the peace process and all this stuff.
And then he says,
"You know,
I was supposed to be the Secretary of
State."
And I thought, "Oh, no. Oh, no."
And he says, "I invited President Obama
to my house for Christmas."
So, this is like four five weeks before
Richardson.
And
he said, "Uh
they're sitting there having a having a
little drink and Obama says, 'John,
if you endorse me and you can bring the
Kennedy family along,
Secretary of State.'
So, Kerry, nobody remembers this, Kerry
was the first senator to endorse Obama
and a week later the whole Kennedy
family endorses Obama. It was a big deal
because Kerry was close to the to the
Clintons and both Kerry and and Hillary
were on the Senate Foreign Relations
Committee together.
And he says, "But, uh you know, that's
Washington politics. I got screwed." So,
afterwards I said, "Senator, you can't
say in public
that you were you were supposed to be
Secretary of State." I said, "Bill
Richardson tells exactly the same
story."
I said, "Obama promised half a dozen
people in Washington that they would be
Secretary of State."
He promised uh
what's-his-face that that
died at the
at the State Department. I forget his
name now. The special negotiator for
Yugoslavia. Anyway, he's promising
everybody they're going to be Secretary
of State.
That was the one time. He goes, "I know,
I'm still bitter. I can't help it."
The other time,
I get a call from the Lebanese
ambassador.
And he's like,
"What's your boss's problem?" I said,
"Well, now what did he do?"
He says,
"He gave an interview
and he keeps calling Bashar al-Assad my
dear friend Bashar al-Assad."
I said, "I I'll talk to him."
So, I said, "Senator,
I said, 'The Lebanese ambassador called
me.
And you have to stop calling Bashar
al-Assad my dear friend.'"
And he's like, "Well, he is my dear
friend." And I said,
"Be that as it may,
he's a genocidal maniac who just wipes
out entire swaths of his population."
And he goes, "Well, you know, we rode
motorcycles together down to the Golan
Heights and and we exchanged you know, a
kind of a a relationship." I said, "I I
I get it. He's probably a lovely guy,
but he's he's a genocidal dictator."
He's like, "All right, all right. Tell
the Lebanese get off my back."
So, it's like, dude,
what are you doing? Another thing about
Kerry, I I've said this a couple times,
but I think it's important enough to
repeat.
When he first called me to offer me this
job, I didn't know this job existed. So,
he calls me and he says,
and I had never met him, but I was
friendly with people who Actually, I
won't I won't give names, but I was
friendly with two guys that he served in
Vietnam with.
And they both said, "Hey, you should
talk to John Kiriakou."
So, he called me, and he said,
"The Senate Foreign Relations Committee
used to have an investigative function,
but it was it was zeroed out in 1972,
and I'm going to bring it back, and I
want to do hard-hitting investigations."
And I said, "That sounds like my sweet
spot."
So, he said, "Why don't you come up,
we'll have a chat, we can see if we're a
fit for one another." I said, "Great." I
put on a suit, I go up to his office.
You walk into his office, he was in the
the Russell Senate Office Building, the
historic office building with the 15-ft
ceilings.
Literally from the floor to the ceiling
were framed pictures of him
with every world leader who matters,
from Gorbachev to the Dalai Lama to the
Pope to everybody.
I was like, "Okay, kind of narcissistic,
but all right, he's a senator and a
presidential candidate, and you know,
big war hero."
I didn't even care about that.
But you walk into the office, and
immediately next to the door there was a
small credenza. It had three things on
it.
First, it had a framed picture of him
with John Lennon, and they're like in
this weird embrace making funny faces
and like doing noogies, right?
Very cool. John Lennon, right? Beatle,
very cool.
On the other side of the credenza was a
picture of him with Peter, Paul, and
Mary, the the folk group from the '60s.
And he was close to them, he gave the
eulogy at Mary Travers' funeral. I get
it, they're all from Massachusetts.
But in the middle
was a shadow box,
and in it had his
Silver Star,
um
his Bronze Stars,
and his Purple Heart.
Well,
in 1972,
he famously threw his medals over the
White House fence to protest the Vietnam
War. It was national news that this hero
just came back from Vietnam, testified
before for Senate Armed Services
Committee, and in an act of defiance,
threw his medals at Richard Nixon, you
know, over the White House fence.
So,
we agreed I'm going to do the job. It's
going to be fun. He wants me to
investigate this, that, and the other
thing. I walk out.
The the staff director of Foreign
Relations Committee was a member
of the Kennedy family.
So, we're walking out and that was
really my connection. I knew him.
And he said, "So, it went well?" And I
said, "Yeah, it went well. I'm I'm going
to take the job." But I said, "I got to
ask you,
what's up with the medals?"
I mean, everybody in America knows he
threw his medals over the White House
fence. He goes, "The medals.
He didn't throw the medals over the
White House fence.
He went to the PX and bought copies of
the medals
and threw the copies over the White
House fence. He goes, "Those medals are
the most important thing in his life.
He would never have thrown his medals
over the fence." I said, "The entire
John Kerry mystique
is based on that one act of defiance."
He goes, "Yeah, well, welcome to
Washington."
You would think maybe you'd leave the
medals at home in a shadow box?
>> Exactly.
>> Not in the office for everyone to see?
You know, he he was really very
cold in a in a patrician, Yankee, New
England kind of way. He had a Christmas
party at his house that year. It was
Christmas of '09.
He lived in this
rare single-family home in Georgetown
that he later sold for 12 and 1/2
million dollars.
Georgetown doesn't have more than a
small handful of single-family homes.
But he wouldn't allow anybody in the
house. It's December
in Washington. It's 20°. So, it has a
side yard surrounded by a brick wall.
Um and he just
rented these
these propane heaters.
So, we're all standing out there.
And um
and he says,
"Well, we have a special guest that's
going to come to the party tonight."
We're all like, you know, this, trying
to keep warm cuz
these heaters aren't doing the trick.
And then
and then Joe Biden comes.
He was vice president at the time. So,
Biden comes and Biden was exactly the
opposite of Kerry. Biden's standing at
the at the entrance to the backyard of
the side yard. HE GOES, "HEY!" LIKE
THIS. EVERYBODY'S LIKE, "HEY, MR. Vice
President. Good to see you."
So, he comes down
and um starts shaking hands with
everybody one at a time. Great eye
contact. Uh "Hi, Joe Biden. Tell me your
name again." You know, that kind of
thing.
I said, "Mr. Vice President, we've met a
number of times. You probably don't
remember me. I'm from Newcastle,
Pennsylvania, and my dad was best
friends with Angelo Sands." He goes,
"Angelo Sands from seventh grade?" And I
said, "Yeah, your best friend from
seventh grade." He says, "I do remember
you. We talked about Angelo's a taxi
driver in Las Vegas now." I said,
"That's right. He is a taxi driver.
Great memory." I said, "That
conversation was 15 years ago."
And then he says to the guy next to me,
"I remember you.
I don't like you."
And he looks at Kerry and he Kerry just
is like,
like, "I don't like him either."
And they walk away. I said to the guy,
"What the fuck?"
He said, "Biden has hated me since I
told him in a memo that we should pull
out of Afghanistan."
And I said, "Sweethearts these guys
are."
And he's like, "Yeah, well, what are you
going to do?"
Washington, D.C. Every man for himself.
Harry Truman once said,
"If you want a friend in Washington, buy
a dog."
There it is.
Did Do any other occurrences? We talked
about We talked about your um
uh your meeting with Bill Clinton.
But Biden, did you have any other like
funny occurrences like that with any
like prominent world leaders or
Oh, yeah, a couple.
Yeah, the Prime Minister of
the Prime Minister of Bahrain did not
like me not even a little bit.
So, I was the human rights officer for
the embassy. And I took him to the
woodshed.
And you know, I mean, in a perfect
world, it would have jeopardized arm
sales
unless they would clean up their act.
So, he had like surveillance on me. I
found a bug in my house. It was bad.
So, Admiral Crowe, who who had been the
um
Chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff,
comes to Bahrain. And
they drew my name out of the hat, so I
was going to be Admiral Crowe's control
officer. Control officer arranges all
the meetings, arranges the
transportation, serves as the note taker
in the meetings.
So, we go to see His Majesty the Emir.
And the Emir was just the sweetest
sweetest old guy you could ever
encounter.
And we finished the meeting.
And um
and we get up
to walk out of the Emir's diwan, his his
meeting room.
And as we get to the elevators, a
private elevator that goes straight from
the Emir's garage into the diwan.
The elevator opens and the Prime
Minister walks out with the Minister of
Interior. Now, the Minister of Interior
is the guy I'm actually taking the
woodshed. The Minister of Interior was
also a prince who was the Prime
Minister's son-in-law.
Right?
So,
so I said, "Oh, I said, Admiral Crowe,
this is His Highness uh
Emir
I'm sorry Prince Khalifa Al Khalifa.
He's the
the Prime Minister.
And uh this is His Highness, you know,
minister I forget what the minister's
name was.
He was married to the prime minister's
daughter.
And uh the prime minister shakes his
hand, and then I said,
as I always said, it's such a pleasure
to see you again, Your Highness. And I
shook his hand, and he wouldn't let my
hand go.
And he's smiling at me, and the
handshake becomes more
like deliberate, like he will not let my
hand go.
And so, we're just standing there
looking at each other.
And he says, I have my eye on you,
Kyriacou. And I said, yes, Your
Highness, I would expect nothing less.
And then I took my hand back. We got in
the elevator, and Admiral Crowe looks at
me, and the ambassador says, what the
hell was that all about?
And I said, last week, they beat to
death a 15-year-old boy for marching in
a pro-democracy democracy demonstration.
And I've been talking to human rights
attorneys and saying I'm going to write
this up for the human rights report, and
they don't like it. And I'm bitching
about [clears throat] it at parties, and
they have my house bugged, and they're
listening to me [__] about it at my
wife or to my wife.
And I think that they just think that
that's somehow is intimidating.
It's not. Well, when I left the country
a year later,
the emir and the prime minister would
always give gifts to to the officers
leaving. We can never accept the gifts.
So, it's usually a Rolex, usually. When
the ambassador left, they they gave him
a cigar box, and it he's like, oh,
cigars. And he opened it up in front We
always had to open the gifts in in the
presence of a witness, right? Cuz then
you have to send the whole thing in the
diplomatic pouch to the Treasury
Department, cuz you can't keep anything
worth more than $25.
So,
he opens the box, and it's $50,000 in
cash.
And the ambassador's like, I'm not
touching it. So, the uh the DCM, the
deputy chief of mission, and the head of
public affairs counted it like with the
wit- the rest of us as witnesses, and
then we just boxed it back up and sent
it to Treasury.
So, I was the only one, the only one who
didn't get a Rolex when we left.
>> [laughter]
>> I thought you would have gotten to keep
it anyway. Yeah, I could have kept it
anyway, but you know.
So, yeah, let's let's end it on a little
bit of a different note. So, one of the
main comments on any YouTube video that
you're a part of is like how good of a
storyteller you are.
>> Oh, thank you. Uh raconteur raconteur is
the words that a lot of people use, but
let's see if I can monetize that. Yeah,
right. Um but anyway, so what how would
you how would you recommend to people to
become more articulate, become a better
storyteller, and just like speak well in
general? How can people get better at
that?
That's a great question.
Um
I'll answer it by beginning with a
story.
>> [laughter]
>> My brother My brother and I went out one
time. We were
like in college, I guess. We went out
something happened. I don't remember
what.
And we got home, and my mom said, "Oh,
so how was it? How was your afternoon?"
I said, "Oh, listen to this." And I told
her what happened. My brother goes,
"That's not what happened."
I said, "That's exactly what happened."
He goes, "Yeah, but it wasn't as
interesting as that."
And I said,
"It's not my fault that you can't tell
an interesting story."
Um
I had a station chief. Oh, wait, he
wasn't my station chief. He was a buddy
of mine who was a station chief. And he
asked me to do an operation
on his behalf because it was too
dangerous for him.
And I didn't live in that country, so I
would just go back and forth to do the
operation. And then I would go directly
from the meeting to the airport and fly
back to the United States. So, I would
do the reporting cables from
headquarters and then send them out to
the field to him. And he called me one
day and he said, "I so love your cables
because I feel when I'm reading them
like I'm standing in the room watching
it go down."
And I said, "Man, that's the biggest
compliment anybody's ever paid me."
I I just enjoy telling stories.
I think everybody has great stories. And
this is why I've written this most
recent series of books. I I have the
series books coming out soon on on
cemeteries and historic graves. I've one
on the mafia graves of New York City,
for example, because
everybody's got a story to tell.
You don't have to be famous. You don't
have to be, you know, special in any
way. Everybody
has a story. And so, I enjoy telling
those stories.
There's no real trick to it, to tell you
the truth.
Just recount it as you recall it. I try
to be linear. I try to do it
I try to recount the story in the order
in which it happened. I I find that to
be helpful.
But there's otherwise no real trick to
it.
So, it sounds like storytelling is is
kind of [clears throat] like innate. But
as far as it is one thing to be
articulate in my position when I ask a a
quick and ideally direct question, but
when you're talking for 6 hours and
there's there's no ums, there's no ahs.
I say like a lot, which is bad. There's
none of that.
>> you know. Yeah, but that one I feel is
acceptable. So, that specifically is
there something like it is it reading?
Is it like is it doing the speaking as
far as repetitions? Like how can people
build that up?
>> I had a
uh speech teacher
in 10th grade, Dr. uh Dr. Scarvel.
He was my dad's best friend growing up.
In fact, he had a glass eye.
He and my dad, when they were 9 years
old, went hunting for squirrels
in Farrell, Pennsylvania. And Dr.
Scarvel tripped on a log and dropped the
the BB gun
and it went off and it shot his eye out.
And so, my dad like carried him to the
nearest house.
So, when I went to the class, he's like,
"Are you Chris Kiriakou's son?" I said,
"Yeah." He said, "You know, he was my
best friend growing up."
He was one of the toughest teachers I
ever had, and it was just speech and
debate.
And so,
we started off with little things like
reading passages from a book, and I knew
I won him over. I still think about this
sometimes.
He says,
"Find a 5-minute passage from a book
and present it as a talk.
Right? You can read it. You don't have
to memorize it, but present it."
To get us into the habit of not saying
um uh
well uh
mm.
So,
all these girls went before us, the
boys, and they're like, "This book is
about love.
This book is about
family." It's like, ay ay ay. I read a
passage from um
from Midnight Express,
the book Midnight Express, about being
beaten in a Turkish prison.
The whole thing was about this
beating
that uh
I forget his name now, uh got at the
hands of these Turkish jailers.
And he stood up and just started doing
the slow clap like this, and he's like,
"That That is what I wanted to hear."
Brad Davis.
So, um
that that class that year taught me not
to stumble over my words.
If you need a filler,
allow silence to be the filler.
There's nothing wrong with that.
You don't have to say uh
well um let me see uh
People hate that.
So, just let silence fill the fill the
time. It doesn't It's not going to harm
you in any way.
And then, he's the one who encouraged me
to go into competitive debate, and I
ended up doing really well in that.
That's where you have to think It Mine
was contemporaneous debate. So, you had
to think quickly on your feet. Like
you
you pull a topic out of a hat, you have
5 minutes to prepare. And then you go on
and just start fighting.
So,
that got me used to answering questions
without any real preparation.
And that lasted all through high school.
I I really credit him
with uh making me
the speaker that I became. Well, yeah,
dude, that'll do it. You know, if you're
It's like if you
They say uh one of one of the guys that
I I watch about um like how to get
better at shooting.
Mhm. And [clears throat] uh basically
they the the premise is like you you
push it as hard as you can in training.
And like everybody wants to leave the
range with a fist-sized group. But you
don't learn anything from that. You just
know that that's how good you can shoot.
So, it's like How do you You want to
learn how to drive 130 miles an hour?
What do you do? You drive 200 miles an
hour. So, that you're comfortable in a
podcast when you've been in debates
already. That is exactly right. Anything
today that I didn't ask you about that
uh that you've thought of or is top of
mind or that you want to talk to people
about?
Dude, you have great questions all the
time.
All the time. That's why I so enjoy
coming on this show.
It's a great conversation. I appreciate
it. Thank you. If you'll let me to uh
pitch
a couple things that I have going on.
Oh, yeah. I'm very proud to have two
podcasts. One is called DeProgram. It's
with Ted Rall and John Kiriakou.
Uh we're going every day starting next
week
at 5:00 on YouTube.
And uh it's
it's far more of a
of a news show. But it's light at the
same time. Ted
is a two-time Pulitzer Prize finalist um
editorial cartoonist.
And then I have another one called Deep
Focus with John Kiriakou. It's much more
in the weeds, in-depth news stuff. I
have great guests. I've been very
fortunate so far. I have uh
See here, and I'm doing it saying um I
have Roger Waters next week from Pink
Floyd. Roger's been one of the most
outspoken supporters of Palestinian
human rights and I'm proud to call the
man a friend.
You know, little secret about Roger
Waters?
He anonymously
paid off my second mortgage when I went
to prison.
Anonymously.
It was years
before I found out that Roger did it.
Like magic, we get this letter from the
bank saying somebody had paid off our
second mortgage. So, my wife and kids
didn't lose the house. Wow. Mhm.
Yeah. One of the founders of Pink Floyd
and a giant in my mind. Mhm. Talk about
generous.
I had never met the man.
But he followed my case, thought I did
the right thing
and put his money where his mouth was.
All right, so deep program, deep focus,
and then the books as well. A lot of
books. Uh I've written eight books. The
eighth was supposed to The eighth was
supposed to be out weeks ago. I'm
yelling at my publisher right now.
Uh but I've got
Well, some The first The first one is
out of print now. It was
What was the name of my first book?
>> Uh The Reluctant Spy.
>> Spy, thank you. The Reluctant Spy, my
secret life [laughter] in the CIA
I can bang these things I don't sleep
very much. So, I bang these things out.
The Reluctant Spy, my secret life in the
in the CIA's war on terror. I actually
made number five on the New York Times
best sellers list with that.
>> good book.
>> Thank you. Thank you. And the second one
was doing time like a spy,
how the CIA taught me to survive and
thrive in prison. I won two literary
awards for that book.
>> Really? I won the PEN First Amendment
Award,
uh which is one of the big four with the
PEN/Faulkner, the Pulitzer, and the
Edgar Allan Poe.
And I won the Forward Reviews Memoir of
the Year.
And then I did The Convenient Terrorist,
uh Abu Zubaydah and The Weird Wonderland
of America's Secret Prisons.
Then I got a whole bunch of books
commissioned. I did The CIA Insider's
Guide to the Iran Crisis, The CIA
Insider's Guide to Surveillance and
Surveillance Detection, The CIA
Insider's Guide to Lying and Lie
Detection, and The CIA Insider's Guide
to Disappearing and Living Off the Grid.
And then I decided to start writing
books for myself, so I wrote one called
Remains of the Day,
the the
The Remains of the Day, The Definitive
Guide to Washington D.C.'s Historic
Cemeteries,
which was supposed to be out weeks ago.
It's coming soon,
but the editorial board liked it so much
they commissioned four more.
They wanted
The next one I'm halfway done with. It's
called Whispers in the Dirt,
um
the
definitive guide to New York City's mob
graves,
then the historic cemeteries of Chicago,
the country western graves of Nashville,
and the graves of America's most
notorious serial killers.
So, I'm trying to pump them out as fast
as I can. Nice.
I love it, dude. I know
I know The Reluctant Spy, I've seen a
lot of my comments that it's tough for
people to get.
>> Yeah, I I don't know why Random House
doesn't just do a second run. It sucks
cuz that's a really good one, too.
>> it's funny, too. The first two books
were translated into both Spanish and
Greek.
They made number one, both of them, on
the Athens bestsellers list.
And then
just two weeks ago I got another check
from the Greek publisher that it's going
to a second printing.
So, they're still buying it in Greek. I
don't know why nobody cares in the
United States.
You can't even find it on eBay anymore.
It's like $100, $200. It's nuts.
Just keep your eyes peeled for it,
folks. Maybe you might find one, but uh
[__] dude. This is uh God, every time I
I get to see you, I have so much fun.
And like
>> have a blast.
>> And I know people enjoy it. So, dude,
like I could sit here and talk to you
for 6 hours.
>> I appreciate it. We'll have to have you
back. But, um
>> Love it.
Yeah, and and I just want to say I
wasn't planning on it, but we were
talking about a bit about it off camera,
and I just feel like speaking to your
character because, um like dude, you you
changed my life like with that very
first interview.
>> And I'll I'll keep this short, but dude,
like when when you and I met, I didn't
have a following. I didn't have a
podcast. I didn't even have a [__]
YouTube channel. Nothing. And what did
you do but you drove here 4 hours from
DC. You sat with me for 7 hours and
drove four back without so much as
asking like, "Hey, what's your
following? What's your exposure?" Yeah.
And like, dude, I met you at the Danny
Jones podcast in Tampa.
And we had such a good conversation,
especially at the airport on the way
back.
>> Yeah. That when you asked me, I said I'd
be delighted to do it. And then,
actually, you changed my life because
that interview that you and I did was so
long and so
extensive
that it came to the attention of a
speakers bureau in London
that then signed me for an
around-the-world speaking tour
>> [laughter]
>> that we're going to pick up again
in January. So,
good for us.
>> Dude, you deserve it.
>> You deserve success.
>> Thank you. And again, man, like I had I
had no following and almost we're coming
up on 2 years later. We're we're coming
up on 300,000 subscribers on the
channel, and like things have been
incredible. So, and again, this show
would be nothing without the guest.
Yeah. But, dude, just just thank you. I
felt the need to say that on camera.
>> mine. Thanks. You're the man.
Um
I'll see you again soon. I'm looking
forward to it.
What's up, guys? Thank you so much for
taking the time to watch the interview.
If you got anything out of this video at
all, please like the video, leave me a
comment, tell me what you thought of the
video, uh tell me who you'd like to see
on the show. I really appreciate the
support. It goes a long way on these
platforms, as you guys know. Most
importantly, I have some excellent
interviews coming up in the future that
I'm really, really excited about. So,
please subscribe to the channel so you
don't miss any of them. But, that's it.
Thank you for your support. I really
appreciate it and hope to see you again
soon.